what do you think of the CIA I mean do
we NE do we still do we need it do we
need the CIA no I don't think so there's
so much redundancy in intelligence well
I'm gonna give you a two-part answer
first of all there's so much redundancy
in in intelligence we really don't need
a CIA the Pentagon has an organization
called defense hum Services hum meaning
human intelligence they recruit spies to
steal secrets well guess what that's
exactly what the CIA does so you've got
DOD doing the same thing you've got the
state Department's Bureau of
intelligence and research and the
defense Department's defense
intelligence agency doing um analysis
exactly what the cia's directorate of
intelligence does so there's redundancy
there you have NSA that's doing all of
the the intercepts you've got DARPA
that's doing all the futuristic cool
scientific inventions and stuff like
that you have Myriad organizations that
are doing simpler things like bugs or
disguises or forgeries or you know any
of the stuff that a CIA officer needs to
do on a day-to-day basis so when you've
got multiple organizations all doing
exactly the same thing isn't that kind
of a waste of money and Manpower and
secondly and this is more
important the CIA has gotten literally
every major Global development wrong
since
1947 from the creation of the Bur wall
through the Suz crisis through the
Vietnam War and and the fall of the
Iranian government and and the loss of
the Sha of Iran through you know Iran
Contra and missing 911 and everything in
between they just got it
wrong so why would we even want to keep
going this gigantic multi-billion dollar
organization that doesn't really provide
anything to the National
Security I worked for uh I worked for
Ambassador John negranti when I was at
the United Nations in New York uh more
than 20 years ago he later went on to
become the Director of National
Intelligence and as the ambassador to
the UN he was in a quasi cabinet level
position and so he was allowed to
receive a pdb briefing every day and he
once told me that not one single time
did the president's Daily Brief tell him
something that the Washington Post and
the New York Times didn't tell him an
hour
earlier do we really need it
right yeah yeah it's so interesting so
interesting so so that's kind of an well
the the interesting I think the most
interesting part of what you just said
is I think a lot of people would be
cheering and saying all right the CIA is
gone let's say Trump comes out and says
Ah we're gonna get rid of this we don't
need it we're gonna get rid of the CIA
people would be cheering saying all
right you know it's a new day it's a new
dawn and really it's like no they' just
now this the spies are everywhere else
they just move around just divide them
up divide them up and send them
someplace else that's it yeah so it
wouldn't actually end anything I mean
nothing would change if we got rid of
the CIA is what you're saying you know
George Washington once said that
gentlemen do not read other gentlemen's
mail and so we didn't have an
intelligence organization in our country
until the passage of the National
Security Act of 1947 and even then it
was almost blocked because it was
opposed by Jay Edgar Hoover it was only
because President Truman lied to Hoover
and said to Hoover no no you need to
support this passage because the CIA is
going to be a division of the
FBI it was a clear lie but Hoover
believed it and he said oh okay well if
I'm going to be the director of both the
FBI and the CIA then okay I I'll lift my
objection and it passed and then trumman
was like ha fooled you and the CIA and
the FBI have been at War ever
since yeah and what was the whole point
of the CIA it was to spy on the Russians
right is that what the initial that's
exactly right it was to spy on the
Russians you know Jim Jim pavit he was
the deputy director for operations um
for whom I worked when I was a briefer
and uh he used to say the same very
simple thing all the the time and I
repeat it all the time now in interviews
because it's so true the job of the CIA
is to recruit spies to steal secrets and
to analyze those secrets to provide the
policy maker with the best informed
analysis now they often fail at that but
that's the whole reason at at its root
to have a
CIA so the CIA the the spies themselves
are not actual spies they're recruiting
other spies in other countries to do the
spying is that yeah you know yeah we all
have these wonderful stories that we
like to tell once we leave about the
cool stuff we've done but the truth of
the matter is if if you've got blonde
hair and blue eyes you're not going to
infiltrate
alqaeda right you're gonna have to
recruit you're gonna have to recruit
some guy from Yemen or from Egypt to do
it for you yeah that's that's really how
it works you recruit the spies to steal
the secrets for
you my favorite family member he's
passed away now but he was my great
uncle and uh my my grandmother's uh
brother and he was in the CIA he was one
of the very earliest first guys in the
CIA he never said he wasn't you know we
we all we found out uh especially later
after he died you know that it was it I
think then it's like no longer it's kind
of like this family secret that's not
really that secret sort of a thing like
we all know Uncle Alton was in the CIA
kind of a thing and he would just
disappear for weeks on end and then come
back with like random Russian
people oh
yeah oh yeah you can say I mean it's a
little bit of an exaggeration but it was
it was it was like that I mean it was he
would disappear for weeks on end and uh
and my grandma's like oh he's off Russia
again or something the CIA and he's
involved in all that stuff and oh I
can't tell you how many times how many
times I went on on missions and I was
instructed to throw away all of my money
before I left the country because I
couldn't risk anybody seeing like whoa
where you got money from XYZ country
what were you doing there H you can't
risk that so at the airport just as I
was getting ready to you know board the
plane which was oftentimes in a fake
passport from some other country so that
there's literally no record of me having
been in that country I'd have to throw
away all my money and all my receipts
yeah wow were you able to tell people
you were in the CIA when you were in it
no so what do you guys say I mean he
said his cover was always that he worked
for NASA I think is what he said that's
a good cover I think that's a good cover
yeah he's like I work in I work for NASA
yeah mine was the state department I
would just say state department and uh
if people pressed I would say ah it's
really boring I'm involved in Fr that's
what he would say sometimes are you guys
trained to say that cuz that's literally
what he would say it's really boring I
just do paperwork I that's it you want
to make the response yeah you want to
make the response so boring that people
don't follow up I'll tell you what I was
on a plane once from Milan to Sophia
Bulgaria and I never talk to people on
planes I just listen to music or read a
book or whatever and I'm sitting next to
this this enormous guy and he would not
shut his mouth for the whole dog on
flight and he kept talking and talking
and finally says so what do you do for a
living I said uh
I'm a businessman oh what kind of
business are you in I said i' import
export you know oh what do you Import
and Export ah whatever was GNA make me
some money I said I whatever it is I can
get a deal on oh like what he says and
he just wouldn't stop so I said
look I smuggle women in cigarettes from
Eastern Europe you happy
now and he says and that was actually
true because yeah right it pretty much
no it wasn't true I and he goes I don't
approve I said well I didn't ask your
approval did I how about shut the [__]
up and then he didn't say a word the
rest of the flight oh so sometimes
that's what you have to
do now I know if somebody starts giving
me vague answers I'll be like oh CIA
okay got it yeah yeah that's right yeah
training and imports and and yeah we do
a lot of exactly yeah yeah interesting
interesting but it so yeah I guess
that's that's um unfortunate to know
that if we got rid of it it doesn't
really go away it just shifts it just it
just morphs into a different agency I
think that that's right because a lot of
us want to see that power that kind of
clandestine power um we somehow we've
got to bring the power back to the
people we've got to yeah and it's we've
got to and you know how we do that we we
do that with with real oversight
committees you know we've got the Senate
select committee on intelligence and the
house permanent select committee on
intelligence which for a brief period
from
1975 to about 1986 were actual real
oversight committees telling the CIA no
you can't do that that's a violation of
international law and now the Committees
really are are little more than
cheerleaders for the CIA and I'll give
you an
example um I went to prison for 23
months after blowing the whistle on the
cia's torture program and when I got out
of prison I was in invited to a dinner
at the Greek ambassador's residence and
Senator Ron weiden of Oregon the
Democrat of Oregon was at the
dinner and um and he came up to me and
he said hey welcome home so glad to hear
that you're out you know blah blah blah
you did this Brave thing and I said
Senator with all due respect I gotta
tell you I actually expected a little
bit more support from you and he got
angry and he said look it took all my
energy just to not lose my security
clearance and I thought oh you're afraid
of them you're not overseeing them
you're afraid of them well if he's the
only one on the Senate intelligence
committee who's viewed by the the media
as you know the one guy who's going to
stand up to the agency what does that
say about all the other members of the
Senate intelligence committee not to
even mention the house intelligence
committee they're all cheerleaders we
need real people we need we need Daniel
Patrick Monahan to come back to life or
Frank church or Ted Kennedy who had the
guts to stand up to these guys and and
those those members of Congress just
don't exist anymore thanks for watching
this clip from the full Kim iveron show
if you want to watch the full show visit
Kim Iverson show.com the show airs every
Monday through Friday at 5: Pacific 8:00
P.M Eastern again it's Kim Iverson
show.com see you there